Zhiyuan Ge

CURRICULUM VITAE

Updated at July 2020

Personal Information

Assistant professor, China University of Petroleum (Beijing)

Department of Geology, College of Geosciences

Changpin District, Beijing, China **Email:** gezhiyuan@cup.edu.cn **Phone:** +86 15901127735

Website: https://geogezhiyuan.com/



I am an assistant professor at College of Geosciences, China University of Petroleum (Beijing). I mainly use subsurface data analysis, analogue modelling and numerical simulation to study the tectono-stratigraphic evolution of sedimentary basins, particularly where the salt-controlled structures and deep-water sedimentary systems interact. I have worked closely with industry on multiple research projects in the last couple of years. Currently I am involved in a research project between University of Bergen and German Research Centre for Geosciences (GFZ) focusing on salt tectonics in passive margins. I have published over 10 peer-reviewed articles in international geoscience journals.

Educational Diplomas

2015 PhD, Department of Earth Science, University of Bergen, Norway

2010 MS, Department of Earth Sciences, Royal Holloway, University of London, UK

2009 BS, Department of Earth Sciences, Zhejiang University, China

Employment

Assistant professor

2020.06 – present Department of Geology, College of Geosciences, China University of

Petroleum (Beijing), China

Postdoc researcher and PhD co-supervisor

2016.07 – 2019.11 Department of Earth Science, University of Bergen, Norway

Teaching assistant

2013.09 – 2014.06 Department of Earth Science, University of Bergen, Norway

Research assistant

2010.10 – 2011.10 Department of Earth Sciences, Royal Holloway, University of London, UK

Research Visit

E.ON Stipendienfonds, EPOS TNA & L. Meltzers Høyskolefond

2019.07 & Helmholtz Laboratory for Tectonic Modelling, German Research

2018.06 – 2018.09 Centre for Geosciences (GFZ), Germany

Internship

2008.08 Seismology Bureau of Zhejiang Province, China

Membership of Professional Affiliations

Member of the American Association of Petroleum Geologists Member of the International Association of Sedimentologists

Research Project

Project leader (PI)

- 1. EON Foundation and EPOS (European Plate Observing System) sponsored project, 'Minibasin evolution in passive margin salt basins', 2018;
- 2. University of Bergen, SPIRE project, 2017–2018;

Project investigator

- 1. Statoil (now Equinor) sponsored project, 'Turbidites, Topography and Tectonics (T³): understanding the response of turbidity currents to structurally controlled seafloor topography', 2016 to present.
- Total Norge AS sponsored project, 'Late Jurassic tectono-stratigraphic development of the Norwegian Central Graben and the influence of normal faulting on turbidite sedimentation', 2011– 2015.
- 3. PetroBras sponsored project, 'Kinematics and Mechanics of Salt-related Fold & Fault Structures in South-Atlantic Passive Margin Sedimentary Basins', 2009 2011.

Conferences

- 1. **Ge, Z.**, Warsitzka, M., Rosenau, M. & Gawthorpe, R.L. The Impact of Instant Versus Progressive Margin Tilting Upon Passive Margin Salt Basins. AAPG GTW EuroAsian Mature Salt Basins, Krakow, April 2019.
- 2. **Ge, Z.,** Warsitzka, M., Rotevatn, A., Gawthorpe, R.L., Zijerveld, L. & T. Wrona. Extension initiation and localization on minibasin formation in passive margin salt basins. TSG, Bergen, Jan 2019.
- 3. **Ge, Z.**, Rosenau, M., Warsitzka, M. & Gawthorpe, R.L. Kinematic domain partitioning in passive margin salt basins: the myth of translational domain. GeoMod2018, Barcelona, Oct. 2018.
- 4. Howlett, D. M., **Ge, Z.**, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R.L., Rotevatn, A., Response of Unconfined Turbidity Currents to Complex Bathymetry in Deepwater Fold and Thrust Belts. AAPG 2018 ACE, Salt Lack City, May 2018.
- 4. **Ge, Z.**, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R.L., Rotevatn, A., Basani, R. & Hansen, E.W.M. The impact of fault topography on turbidity currents descending from the slope to the floor of an early-stage deep-water rift basin: insights from CFD numerical simulations. IAS 2013. Manchester, Sep. 2013.
- 5. **Ge, Z**., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Wonham, J. Variations in Depocentre Style under Mid-Late Jurassic Salt-Influenced Rifting: Norwegian Central Graben, North Sea. AAPG 2013 ACE, Pittsburgh, May 2013.

Publication List

- 1. Howlett, D.*, Gawthorpe, R., **Ge, Z.**, Rotevatn, A., & Jackson, C. A-L, (2020), Turbidites, Topography and Tectonics: Evolution of submarine channel-lobe systems in the salt-influenced Kwanza Basin, offshore Angola. *Basin Research* (under review)
- 2. **Ge, Z.***, Gawthorpe, R., Zijerveld, L., & Oluboyo, A. P., (2020), Controls on variations of geometry and stratigraphy in salt minibasins: Lower Congo Basin, Angola Margin. *Basin Research*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1111/bre.12486
- 3. **Ge, Z.***, Warsitzka, M., Rosenau, M., & Gawthorpe, R., (2019), Progressive margin tilting controls thin-skinned deformation in salt-bearing basins. *Geology*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1130/G46485.1
- 4. **Ge, Z.***, Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., Zijerveld, L., Jackson, C. A.-L., & Oluboyo, A. P., (2019), Minibasin depocentre migration during diachronous salt welding, offshore Angola. *Basin Research*. doi: https://doi.org/10.1111/bre.12404
- 5. **Ge, Z.***, Rosenau, M., Warsitzka, M., & Gawthorpe, R., (2019), Overprinting translational domains in passive margin salt basins: Insights from analogue modelling. *Solid Earth*. doi: doi.org/10.5194/se-10-1283-2019
- 6. Howlett, D. M.*, Ge, Z., Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Jackson, C. A.-L., (2019) Response of unconfined turbidity current to deep-water thrust fold-belt topography: orthogonal incidence on solitary and segmented folds. *Sedimentology*. doi: 10.1111/sed.12602
- 7. **Ge, Z.***, Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Ernst, H., (2018) Response of unconfined turbidity current to relay-ramp topography: insights from process-based numerical modelling. *Basin Research*, doi:10.1111/bre.12255
- 8. **Ge, Z.***, Gawthorpe, R., Rotevatn, A., & Thomas, M., (2017) Impact of normal faulting and pre-rift salt tectonics on the structural style of salt-influenced rifts: the Late Jurassic Norwegian Central Graben, North Sea. *Basin Research*, doi:10.1111/bre.12219
- 9. **Ge, Z.*,** Nemec, W., Gawthorpe, R., & Ernst, H., (2017) Response of unconfined turbidity current to normal-fault topography. *Sedimentology*, 64: 932–959. doi:10.1111/sed.12333
- 10. Adam, J.*, **Ge, Z.,** & Sanchez, M. (2012). Salt-structural styles and kinematic evolution of the Jequitinhonha deepwater fold belt, central Brazil passive margin. *Marine and Petroleum Geology*, 37(1), 101-120. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2012.04.010
- 11. Adam, J.*, **Ge, Z.,** & Sanchez, M. (2012). Post-rift salt tectonic evolution and key control factors of the Jequitinhonha deepwater fold belt, central Brazil passive margin: Insights from scaled physical experiments. *Marine and Petroleum Geology*, 37(1), 70-100. doi: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.marpetgeo.2012.06.008